本字幕由 启点字幕组 献上
翻译：Apple Lisa、捉鬼的蛋包饭
翻译：腹黑老莲子、洞洞、自然卷
翻译：Linette、虫子、sei
时间轴：罐头宝宝小CC
这个杀手不太冷
校对：温泉の玉子、这个CC不太冷、新鲜爽口芦荟汁、乌鸦投石子想喝葡萄汁
后期：牧好好
总监：打雷天西瓜汁和玉子烧更配哟(づ￣ 3￣)づ
最近怎么样 里昂
- Allora, come stai, Leone?
挺好的
Bene.
好吧 我们来谈点正经事儿
Okay, okay. Let's talk business.
这个死胖子插手了
This fat bastard is moving in
莫里奇奥的买卖
on Morizio's business.
你知道莫里奇奥是讲道理的
You know Morizio is a reasonable guy.
他只想谈谈
He just wants a little conversation.
但这家伙 他不想听
But this guy, he don't wanna hear about it.
或许他会听你的
Maybe he'll listen to you.
他每周二来镇上
He comes to town every Tuesday.
你周二有空吗
Are you free Tuesday?
嗯 有空
Yeah, I'm free Tuesday.
真高兴再见到你 琼斯先生
Nice to see you again, Mr.  Jones.
记住 办得利落点 给你半小时
Remember, neatness counts. You got one half hour.
一小时
One hour.
怎么了
Yea...  What?
我是楼下的唐托
It's Tonto, downstairs.
这儿有个人想跟你谈谈
There's a guy wants to talk to you.
他长什么样
What's he look like?
蛮严肃的
Serious.
告诉他我要上来了
Tell him I'm coming up.
他要上来了
He's coming up.
有人来了 来者不善
Somebody's coming up.  Somebody serious.
米基
Mickey,
眼睛擦亮点 有人来砸场儿了
open your eyes.  We got company.
有人来砸场儿了
We got company.
来吧
Come on.
住手 快住手
Stop! Stop, man!
唐托
Tonto.
叫在外面等我们的司机回来 赶紧的
Tell the driver to wait for us out back, and hurry up.
亲爱哒 肿么啦
Hey sweetie, what's going on?
宝贝 别担心 没事儿 你再歇会儿吧
Don't worry, baby. It's cool.  Take a nap.
天哪
Oh, my God.
这些混蛋把两个出口都堵了
Those fuckers blocked both the exits.
去检查阳台
Check the terrace!
这里是911紧急热线
911 emergency.
救命 有人要杀我
I need help.  Somebody's trying to kill me.
请别挂机 马上帮您转接
Alright.  Just stay on the line.  I'll just be off a moment.
先生 即将为您接通一个警官
Sir, I'm gonna connect you with an officer.
我是杰弗逊警探 有什么需要帮助的吗
Detective Jefferson.  May I help you?
待会儿再打给你
I'll call you back.
兄弟 放松点
Relax, man.
那边手提箱里的毒品可以买下半个玻利维亚
I got half of Bolivia sitting in them suitcases.
还没勾兑过
Hasn't even been cut yet.
去吧 拿走吧 都归你
Go ahead, take it. It's yours.
拨这个号码
Dial this number.
亲爱的 我们回头再约哈
I'll talk to you later, sweetie, okay?
拜拜
Bye.
你好
Hello?
我是莫里奇奥 还记得我吗
It's Morizio.  Remember me?
我知道你回镇上了
I see you're back in town.
嗯 哦不 我的意思是 就待今天一天
Yeah.  I mean, no. Just for today.
那不妨说今天也是你在镇上的最后一天
So it's safe to say today's your last day in town...
我们再也不用看到你那张肥猪脸了
and we'll never see your fat fucking face again.
对对对
Yeah.  Right.
让我跟咱们共同的朋友说两句
Let me speak to our mutual friend.
他要你接电话
He wants to talk to you.
嗯
Yeah.
确保他明白我的意思 然后让他滚
Make sure he understands, and let him go.
你明白了吗
Do you understand?
说出来
So say it.
我明白了
I understand.
很好
Good.
苍天啊
Jesus.
照例两盒牛奶吗
Two milk as usual?
嗨
Hi
你为什么把烟藏起来
Why did you hide the cigarette?
楼里到处是耗子
This building's full of rats.
我可不想我家老头儿发现
I didn't want my old man to find out.
麻烦够多了
Got enough problems.
怎么弄的
What happened?
骑自行车摔的
I fell off my bike.
不要告诉我爸香烟的事儿 好吗
Don't tell my dad about the cigarette, okay?
- 你为什么这么对我们 - 我真的不知道
- Why are you doing this to us? - I don't know...
现在人都很健忘的
People got memory problems these days.
一定是太阳把脑子烧坏了
It must be the sun.
少晒点太阳 好好想想
Know when to come out of the sun.
我不知道怎么会发生这种事
I don't know how it happened.
我只负责保管
What's my job? I'm just a holder.
保管你们给我的东西
I hold the stuff you give to me.
不看 不碰
I don't look at it or touch it.
我甚至不知道怎么稀释
I don't know how to cut it.
听着
Try to follow me.
我们六月份给你这些毒品
In June, we gave you the dope.
当时纯度还是百分之百
It tests 100 percent pure.
现在七月了 我们再来拿
Now it's July, we pick up the dope,
测出来纯度只有百分之九十
and it tests 90 percent pure.
六月到七月中的某个时间
Somewhere between June and July,
百分之十的纯度不见了
ten percent turned to cut!
我不知道 不关我的事
I don't know.  It's none of my business.
你给了我 我就只负责保管
You give me the stuff, I hold it.
我就知道这么多
That's all I know.
好吧 你看 我在试图拉你出苦海
Look, you know, I'm trying to help you out here...
但你要是再这么嘴硬
but if you're gonna be a hard- ass about it...
我就要去打扰他了
I gotta disturb him.
告诉你
Let me tell you.
他沉浸在音乐中的时候
When he's into his music,
最恨被人打扰了
he hates being disturbed.
我说的都是实话
I'm telling you the truth.
但愿如此
I hope so,
因为他有嗅出谎言的天赋
because he's got a talent for sniffin' out a lie.
很吓人的 就像是第六感
It's scary. It's almost like a sixth sense.
你是要
Are you gonna
改变主意
change your tune
还是要我去麻烦他呢
or I gotta bust into his?
我说的就是实话
I'm telling you the truth.
好吧
All right.
史丹
Stan.
对不起 他说他没稀释毒品
I'm sorry.  He said he didn't cut the dope.
哦
Oh
他当然没有
Of course he didn't.
帮我个忙 明天查出来是谁做的
Just do me a favor. Find out who did by tomorrow.
正午之前
Noon.
马尔奇 等等
Malky, wait.
我又没做 你自己查去吧
I didn't cut your shit. Find out yourself!
你在这儿干嘛
What are you doin' out here?
进去做你的作业
Get inside and do your homework.
我做完了
I did it already.
是吗 那滚进去帮你姐姐
Oh yeah? Get inside and help your sister
打扫下该死的屋子
clean up the goddamn house!
不许再抽烟
And stop smoking cigarettes!
时间到了 该我看了
Time's up.  My turn.
你要是敢换台 我就撕碎你的脸
Change the channel, and I'll smash your face.
抱歉 亲爱的
Sorry, sweetheart.
早 小宝贝儿
Oh Sweetie
嗨 亲爱的 好孩子
Hi, honey, you two.
宝贝 把声音调低点
Sweetheart, turn that down.
妈妈头疼死了
Mama's got a headache.
她占了我的时间
She took my turn.
她要看傻X的动画片
She wants to watch goddamn cartoons!
运动下她屁股又不会死
It wouldn't hurt her to move her ass.
我又不是屁股肥的那一个
I'm not the one with a fat ass around here.
那个整天除了看动画片
Can someone who's doing nothing all day
屁事不做的人
but watching cartoons...
能动下她的小屁屁去弄点吃的吗
move a little ass and go get some food?
有本事再说一遍
I dare you to say that again.
玛姬 我好像搞砸了
Margie, I think I screwed up.
反正也不是第一次了
It wouldn't be the first time.
你总是惹出些麻烦事儿 是吧
You always come up with somethin', right?
我觉得这次越线了
I think I went too far this time.
你现在才叫越线
You're goin' too far right now.
我上班要迟到了
I'm gonna be late for work.
不如今天在家工作吧
How about workin' at home today?
[动画]现在轮到我了
Now it's my turn!
该死 她要打我 爸
Shit! She's gonna hit me! Daddy！
草 把门关上
Shit! Shut the goddamn door!
小贱人
Fuckin' bitch.
谁接下电话
Can somebody answer the phone?
我忙着呢
I'm busy!
喂
Hello?
我是玛格丽特·麦卡利斯特
This is Marguerite McCallister...
新泽西 威尔伍德市 斯宾瑟学校的校长
headmistress at the Spencer School in Wildwood, NewJersey.
兰多先生或女士在家吗
Is Mr.  Or Mrs.  Lando home?
在 我就是
Yes, this is she.
兰多女士 当您丈夫在斯宾瑟为玛蒂尔达注册时
Mrs.  Lando, when your husband enrolled Mathilda at Spencer...
他告诉我们她有点"问题"
he told us she had "Problems. "
正如您所知 我们致力于
As you know, we pride ourselves on
将问题少女们培养成健康 有成就的年轻女性
turning troubled girls into healthy, productive young women.
但是如果她们人都不在这 我们能做的就非常少了
But if they are not here, there is very little we can do.
大约两个星期前 玛蒂尔达未经允许离开了学校
Mathilda left school without permission nearly two weeks ago.
我知道您的丈夫预付了一年学费
I know your husband paid tuition in advance for a year...
但是如果您去查阅
but if you will refer to the page 20
我们寄给您的学生守则第20页
in the rules and regulations manual we sent you...
您就会发现 长期缺席者
you will see that unless there is a valid excuse
除非有正当理由 学费将不会退回
for prolonged absence your tuition will be forfeit.
她死了
She's dead.
叫那混蛋小孩来做点儿事
Tell that fuckin' kid to do a little work around here!
打扫干净 我真是受够了这堆垃圾
Clean up! I'm tired of this fuckin' mess.
快点
Hurry up!
Why am I feeling, when things could look black
为什么当一切看起来不算乐观的时候
电影片段出自歌舞天王吉恩·凯利的《好天气》"It's Always Fair Weather" 歌曲名为《I Like Myself》
That nothing could possibly go wrong
我却觉得生活依旧美好
This has been a most unusual day
这已经成为最特别的一天
Love has made me see things in a different way
爱让我们用不同的角度看待人和事
储水管
生活总是这么艰难吗
Is life always this hard,
还是只有童年时才会这样
or is it just when you're a kid?
总是如此
Always like this.
留着吧
Keep it.
我要去小卖铺买点东西 你想要点牛奶吗
Hey, I'm going grocery shopping.  You want some milk?
要一瓶还是两瓶 是两瓶 对吗
One quart or two? It's two, right?
我真喜欢这暴风雨前短暂的平静
I like these calm little moments before the storm.
路德维希·凡·贝多芬: 德国著名的音乐家 维也纳古典乐派代表人物之一
这让我想到了贝多芬
It reminds me of Beethoven.
你能听到吗
Can you hear it?
就像当你附耳到草丛中
It's like when you put your head to the grass...
你可以听到它们生长 听到昆虫爬动
you can hear it growin'. You can hear the insects.
你喜欢贝多芬吗
Do you like Beethoven?
不算喜欢
Couldn't really say.
我来给你演奏一段
I'm gonna play you some.
爸爸
Daddy!
你最好待在这儿
You better stay here.
爸爸 爸
Daddy! Daddy!
背景音乐为艾瑞克·塞拉的原创音乐《Noon》 并非贝多芬的交响乐作品
我们说好了正午
We said noon.
但是已经过了一分钟了
I've got one minute past.
你不喜欢贝多芬
You don't like Beethoven.
你不知道你错过了什么
You don't know what you're missing.
那样的前奏就能让我热血沸腾
Overtures like that get my juices flowing.
充满能量
So powerful.
但是前奏过后 说真的
But after his openings, to be honest...
就开始有点太他妈无聊了
he does tend to get a little fucking boring.
所以我停下了
That's why I stopped!
彻查这间屋子
Toss the apartment.
沃尔夫冈·阿玛多伊斯·莫扎特: 欧洲著名古典主义音乐作曲家
你是莫扎特的粉丝 我也喜欢他
You're a Mozart fan.  I love him too.
我超爱莫扎特的
I love Mozart!
他是奥地利人
He was Austrian, you know.
但是做这种工作 他有点太轻柔了
But for this kind of work, he's a little bit light.
所以我选了些更激烈的
So I tend to go for the heavier guys.
不错诶
Cool.
该死的 你在干什么
Dude, what the fuck are you doing?
马尔库斯的孩子 沸血之矛
闭上你的臭嘴
Man, keep your bombacut mouth shut.
约翰内斯·勃拉姆斯: 德国古典主义最后的作曲家 浪漫主义中期作曲家
你可以试试勃拉姆斯 他也不错
Check out Brahms.  He's good too.
你他妈懂什么音乐
What the fuck do you know about music?
伙计 消停点
Man, knock it off!
你查了床垫吗
You check the mattress?
没有
Nope.
- 噢 该死! - 他已经死了
- Oh! Fuck! - He's dead.
史丹
Stan
天 看你做了什么
Jesus.  Look what you did.
史丹 你还好吗
Stan, you all right?
你看你做了什么
Look what you did.
嘿 史丹 你在做什么
Hey, Stan, Stan, what are you doin'?
你在做什么 他已经死了
What are you doin'.  He's dead!
但是他毁了我的西装
But he ruined my suit.
我知道 但是他已经死了
Yeah, I know, but he's dead.
他现在就是一滩肉 别想了 冷静点
He's a piece of meat.  Forget about it.  Calm down.
我很冷静
I'm calm.
- 在这待着 成吗  - 好的
- Stay there, OK?  - OK
本尼
Benny!
我的天 本尼
Jesus fuckin' Christ, Benny!
我们是马尔奇和史丹
It's Malky and Stan!
放轻松 好吗 来
Take it easy, all right?Come on.
本尼
Benny!
来 去抽根烟 好吗
Come on, let's get a cigarette.  All right?
本尼 我们要过来了
Benny, we're comin' out!
本尼 别开枪
Benny, don't fire!
进去 我的天 本尼
Get in there!Jesus fuckin' Christ, Benny!
你穿了新衣服 有火吗
You wear somethin' new and...  Got a light?
放轻松
Take it easy.
外面发生什么了
What's happening out there?
没什么 夫人 我们是缉毒组的
It's all right, ma'am.  D. E. A.  Police.
放过那可怜的一家吧
Leave that poor family alone.
一切都好着呢 只要你冷静下来
Everything's all right.  Just calm down
我很冷静 我超冷静的
I am calm.  I'm calm.
你们为什么不能放过他们呢
Why don't you leave them alone?
他说了 回你屋去
He said go back inside.
史丹 我觉得我们还是进去比较好
Stan, I think it's better if we go inside.
本尼 把厨房掀了也要给我找出那些东西来
Benny, turn that kitchen upside down! Find that shit!
威利·布拉德 看看你都做了什么
Willy Blood, look what you did!
你杀了一个4岁小孩
You killed a 4- year- old kid!
有必要吗
Did you really have to do that?
求你开开门
Please open the door.
拜托
Please
求你了
本尼 他们家有三个小孩
Benny, there are three kids here.
我觉得史丹杀了这个女孩
I think Stan killed this girl.
混蛋威利 杀了这个小男孩
Willy, that asshole, shot the little boy.
第三个不见了 找到她
The third one's missing.  Find her.
该死 我们丢了那个小女孩
Shit.  We missed the little girl, man.
为了找这小混球我要翻遍这栋楼了
I'm gonna find the fuckin' super in this goddamn building.
- 你不认识我了吗  - 我暴乱兽 知道你
- Don't you recognize me  - Me, Repugnus, know you
哟 我找到了
Yo! I found it!
棒
Bingo!
史丹 他们找到了
Stan, they found it
我知道
I know.
就是这个
There it is.
警察来了 我们最好撤
There's cops outside.  We better go.
警察来了 我们最好撤 你留这
It's the cops outside.  We better go.  You stay here.
你想我怎么跟他们说
What do you want me tell them?
告诉他们
Tell them...
我们是执行公务
we were doing our job.
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
玛蒂尔达
Mathilda
关于你爸爸 我很抱歉
Sorry about your father.
如果他们不杀他
If somebody didn't do it one day or another,
说不定哪天我自己就动手了
I would have probably done it myself.
你妈妈 她
Your mother, she...
她不是我妈妈
She's not my mother.
我姐姐一天到晚就想着减肥
My sister wanted to lose some weight anyway.
但是她从没瘦下来过
Bet she never looked better.
她甚至不是我亲姐
She's not even my real sister.
只有一半是
Just a half sister.
还不是好的那一半
Not a good half at that.
如果你不喜欢他们 你哭什么
If you couldn't stand them, why are you crying?
因为他们杀了我的弟弟
Because they killed my brother.
他到底做错了什么 他才4岁
What the hell did he do? He was four years old.
他以前从来不哭
He never used to cry.
他只会坐在我旁边 靠着我
He just used to sit next to me and cuddle.
比起那头臭母猪
I was more of a mother to him
我更像他的妈妈
than that goddamned pig ever was.
不要这样说猪
Don't talk like that about pigs.
它们通常比人好
They're usually nicer than people.
但它们闻起来臭死了
But they smell like shit.
不对
Not true.
事实上 现在
As a matter of fact, right now
我厨房里就有一头非常干净的 闻起来也很香的猪
I have one in my kitchen that's very clean... it smells very nice.
你厨房里没有猪
You don't have a pig in your kitchen.
我有
Yes, I do.
我刚刚就在那 没有看见什么见鬼的猪
I was just in there, and I didn't see any goddamned pig.
别动 我去找它
Don't move.  I'll get him.
小猪 小猪 你在哪儿
Piggy, piggy where are you?
原来在这儿
There you are.
嗨 玛蒂尔达
Hi, Mathilda.
嗨 小猪
Hi, piggy.
今天过得好吗
How are you today?
并不好
I've seen better days.
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
里昂
Leon.
名字真可爱
Cute name.
你有其他人可以求助
You have anyone to go to,
其他家庭或者地方可去吗
any family anyplace else?
我还得去拿点牛奶
I'm gonna get some more milk.
我的天啊
Holy shit.
别碰那个 拜托
Don't touch that, please.
里昂 你究竟是做什么工作的
Leon, what exactly do you do for a living?
清道夫
Cleaner.
意思是 你是职业杀手
You mean you're a hit man?
嗯
Yeah.
酷
Cool.
无论谁都清除吗
Do you clean anyone?
不杀女人和小孩儿 这是原则
No women, no kids.  That's the rules.
雇人杀掉那些杀了我弟弟的人渣
How much would it cost to hire someone to get those dirtbags...
要花多少钱
who killed my brother?
一个人头五千美金
Five grand a head.
这样好不好 我为你工作
How about this. I work for you...
作为交换 你教我怎么杀人
and in exchange, you teach me how to clean?
你觉得怎么样
What do you think?
我给你打扫屋子 出门采购
I'll clean your place.  I'll do the shopping.
我还会给你洗衣服
I'll even wash your clothes.
干不干
Is it a deal?
不 这买卖我不干
No, it's not a deal.
那你让我怎么办 我没地方可去了
What do you want me to do? I've got no place to go.
你经历了可怕的一天
You've had a rough day today.
去睡一觉 我们明天再商量 好吗
Go to sleep, and we'll see tomorrow,OK?
你对我真好 里昂
You've been really great with me, Leon...
没人对我这么好过
and it's not always like that.
你知道吗
You know?
晚安
Good night.
睡得好吗
You sleep well?
好 吃过早饭之后你就得走了
Good.  After breakfast you gotta take off.
去哪里
Where to?
和我无关
Not my problem.
读这个
Read it.
你不识字
You don't know how to read.
我正在学 但是最近工作太忙
I'm learning, but I've had a lot of work lately...
所以学得有点慢 上面说了什么?
so I'm a little behind. What's it say?
我已经决定这辈子要做什么了
I've decided what to do with my life.
我要做一名清道夫
I wanna be a cleaner.
你想做一名清道夫 给 拿着
You wanna be a cleaner.  Here. Take it.
给你的送别礼 去杀人吧
It's a good- bye gift.  Go clean,
但是别和我一起 我单独行动 明白吗 单独
but not with me.  I work alone.  Understand? Alone.
邦妮·派克和克莱德·巴罗 电影《雌雄大盗》主人公
邦妮和克莱德不会单独行动
Bonnie and Clyde didn't work alone.
塞尔玛和路易斯 电影《末路狂花》主人公 因在旅行中意外杀人而逃亡
塞尔玛和路易斯不会单独行动 而且 她们最厉害
Thelma and Louise didn't work alone.  And they were the best.
玛蒂尔达 你为什么要这么对我
Mathilda, why are you doing this to me?
我一直对你挺好的
I've been nothing but nice to you.
甚至昨天还救了你一命 就在门外面
I even saved your life yesterday, right outside the door.
没错 所以现在你就要为此负责
Right.  So now you're responsible for it.
你既然救了我 你肯定有救的理由
If you saved my life, you must've saved it for a good reason.
如果你现在丢下我
If you throw me out now,
那就相当于你从没开过门
I take it you never opened your door
那时就已让我死在了你门口
like you let me die right there in front of it.
但是 你开了门
But you did open it.
所以
So...
如果你不帮我 今晚我就会死 我能预知到
If you don't help me, I'll die tonight.  I can feel it.
今晚我还不想死
I don't wanna die tonight.
你还只是个小女孩 所以
You're just a little girl, So
别难过 但我不觉得你能当个杀手
Don't take it badly, but I don't think you could do it.
对不起
I'm sorry.
怎么样
How's that?
玛蒂尔达 你要是再敢那么做 我就打爆你的头
Mathilda, don't you ever do that again or I'll break your head.
- 明白了吗 - 好的
- You got that? - Okay.
我不是那样工作的 那不专业
I don't work like that.  It's not professional.
要有原则
There is rules.
好的
Okay.
不要总是说"好的"了 懂吗
And stop saying "Okay" All the time OK?
好的
Okay.
很好
Good.
你打算在旅馆里拉小提琴吗
You expect to use that in this hotel?
先生 我必须要拉 因为
Mister, I have to use it...
茱莉亚音乐学院：美国著名音乐学院 为8至18岁艺术天才提供系统专业的音乐教育
因为 下个月我在茱莉亚音乐学院有一场试演
because I have an audition at Juilliard next month
所以 我必须要练习
and I have to practice.
好吧 不过不能在十点之后
Okay, but not after 10:00.
好的 我保证
Okay, I promise.
好吧 我会把你们安排在走廊尽头
All right. I'll put you at the end of the hall...
这样就不会打扰到别人了
so that you don't disturb anyone.
请您填了这些表格
Fill those out, please.
爸爸
Daddy,
可以让我填表格吗
can I please fill them out?
你知道我很喜欢登记入住信息
You know how I like to check in to hotels.
谢谢爸爸 我很快会把表格拿回来
Thanks, Pop.  I'll bring these back in a minute.
在四楼
The fourth floor!
谢谢您 先生
Thanks, mister!
你很幸运 有一个
You're lucky to have a little girl
对一切都感兴趣的女儿
that's interested in things.
我有个孩子 17岁 整天无所事事
I have a kid, 17, does nothing all day long.
我能把植物留在这儿
Can I leave my plant here
上楼放行李吗
while I take my stuff upstairs?
当然
Of course.
我填的是班里一个我讨厌的女生的名字
I'm putting in a name of a girl in my class who makes me sick.
这样出了麻烦 就由她来担着
If things get hot, she'll take the heat.
给你 填完了
There.  Finished.
你多大了
How old are you?
十八
Eighteen.
Eighteen?
要看看我的身份证吗
Want to see my license?
不用 只是你看上去要小一点
No.  You just look a little younger.
谢谢
Thanks.
里昂 我想让你教我怎么变得和你一样
Leon, I want you to teach me how to be like you.
- 我想像你一样 强大又聪明 - 玛蒂尔达
- I want to be strong and smart like you.  - Mathilda
我知道自己现在还不够强大
I know I'm not strong enough yet...
但是我可以先打基础 从理论学起
but I could learn the basics, the theory.
你觉得呢 只是理论
What do you think? Just the theory.
我需要这么做 里昂 我需要时间稳定情绪
I need this, Leon. I need time to get my head together.
好吧 而我需要
Yeah, and I need...
喝一杯
a drink.
别动 我去给你拿
Don't move.  I'll go get one.
听到你说让我拿这个玩具给你的时候
When you told me to get this baby out for you...
我还以为自己的耳朵出问题了
I thought my hearin' was goin'.
我告诉自己 里昂是专业的
I says to myself, " Leon's a pro.
只有菜鸟才用这东西
Nobody uses that except beginners. "
我想要保持状态
I like to stay in shape.
没错
Sure.
永远掌控一切 和我一样
Always stay on top of it. It's like me.
任何时刻我都要知道所有东西在哪里
I gotta know where everything is all the time.
这就是为什么我从来没离开过这里 除了走来走去
That's why I never leave this place, except to go from here to there.
改变不是件好事 里昂 你懂吗
Change ain't good, Leon.  You know?
嗯
Yeah.
检查一下吧
Check it.
确认这就是你要的
Make sure it's the right thing.
我相信你
I trust you.
一码是一码 事情要分开算
One thing's got nothin' to do with the other.
记住这一点
Remember that.
我会的
I will.
来复枪是你要学习的第一件武器
The rifle is the first weapon you learn how to use...
因为它能让你和目标保持距离
because it lets you keep your distance from the client.
当你越来越专业时
The closer you get to being a pro...
你离目标也就越来越近
the closer you can get to the client.
拿刀来举个例子
The knife, for example,
刀是你要学习的最后一件武器
is the last thing you learn.
明白吗
Okay?
好的
Okay.
找位置
Position.
不对
No.
不到最后一刻 别把镜盖拿下来
Never take it off until the last minute.
它(瞄准镜)会反射光线
It reflects light.
他们在一英里外都能看到你来了
They can see you coming from a mile away.
还有 记得永远穿着低调
And always dress down.
比地板还要暗淡 明白吗
Never brighter than the floor, okay?
好的
Okay.
现在我们来练习 这是学习的最好办法了
Let's practice now.  It's the best way to learn.
我该射谁呢
Who should I hit?
谁都行
Whoever.
我一会就来
I'll be with you in a second.
等我一下
Give me a few minutes.
谢谢
Thank you.
你们怎么就不懂呢 我不要看见你们
You guys get lost.  I don't want to see you.
看上去得自然
This has to look natural.
不杀女人和小孩儿 对吗
No women, no kids.  Right?
对
Right.
那个穿橙黄相间外套 在慢跑的人怎么样
Jogger in the yellow and orange?
可以
Okay.
保持冷静
Keep calm.
视线不要离开目标
Don't take your eyes off him.
放慢呼吸
Breathe easy.
观察他的动作
Watch his movement.
假装你跟他一起在跑
Pretend you're running with him.
试着感受他的下一个动作
Try to feel his next movement.
深呼吸 屏息
Take a deep breath.  Hold it.
开枪
Now.
我没事 我很好
I'm all right.  I'm fine.
趴下
Get down!
一击命中 不错吧
One shot.  Not bad, huh?
现在能用真子弹了吗
Can we try with real bullets now?
今天不行 收工
Not today.  Let's pack up.
就像这样
Like that.
不用 谢了
No, thanks.
没得商量
No discussion.
苏格拉底似乎...
"It seemed to Socrates... "
我来吧
I'll do it.
里昂 我们整天都在工作
Leon, all we do is work.
休息一下 来玩个游戏吧
We need a break.  Let's play a game.
什么游戏
What kind of game?
我有个超棒的游戏
I have this great game.
有助于思考和记忆
It makes you think and helps your memory.
正是你所需要的
It's exactly what you need.
好吧
Okay.
我是谁
Who is it?
歌手麦当娜1984年发行的经典曲目 《Like A Virgin》
不知道
I don't know.
1962年 玛丽莲·梦露为即将迎来45岁生日的肯尼迪总统献唱生日歌
不知道
I don't know.
小胡子
Moustache.
卓别林
不知道
No.
吉恩·凯利在1952年上映的经典电影《雨中曲》中的歌舞表演
吉恩·凯利
Gene Kelly?
答对了
Good.
轮到你了
Your turn now.
好了 你们这些旅客
Okay, pilgrim.
克林特·伊斯特伍德 硬汉明星 被称为"城市牛仔"
克林特·伊斯特伍德
Clint Eastwood?
我不知道 我放弃
I don't know.  I give up.
约翰·韦恩 著名的好莱坞西部片明星
约翰·韦恩
John Wayne.
我刚刚想说
I was just about to say that.
我发誓 太神奇了 里昂 你扮得太像了
I swear.  It's amazing. Leon, really brilliant.
太棒了
Amazing
你很喜欢你的盆栽 对吗
You love your plant, don't you?
它是我最好的朋友
It's my best friend.
永远快乐 无忧无虑
Always happy.  No questions.
就像我一样 没有根
It's like me, you see. No roots.
如果你真喜欢它 就应该把它
If you really love it, you should plant it
种在公园里 让它落地生根
in a park so it can have roots.
里昂
Leon
同样你想让我长大 也该为我浇水
You should be watering me if you want me to grow.
没错
You're right.
它们要能从盘子里跳出来 要够新鲜
They gotta be jumping out of the plate.  They gotta be alive.
好久不见 里昂
It's been a long time, Leon.
我想你了
I missed you.
你也错过了一些好工作
And you missed some nice jobs too.
我在训练
Been training.
训练是好事 但别过头了
Training's good, but don't overdo it.
工作可比训练赚得多 里昂
Training don't pay as good as working, Leon.
托尼
Tony...
我赚的那些钱 你帮我保管的钱
all the money I make, that you keep for me...
你需要用钱吗
You need some money?
我就是问一下
Just curious.
我为你工作这么久
I've been working a long time...
从来没用过那些钱
and I haven't done anything with my money.
我想也许有一天
I thought maybe someday
我会用到它
I could use it.
你有女人了吗
You met a woman.
你要小心女人
You gotta be careful with women.
记得你刚来这个国家的时候吗
Remember when you arrived in this country?
我收留你的时候
When I took you in,
你还是个毛头小子
you were still wet behind the fuckin' ears...
却已经因为女人趟进了浑水
and, already, you were in deep shit because of a woman.
别忘了 里昂
Don't forget that, Leon.
有时我真希望我能忘了
I wish I could sometimes.
你知道 我的钱
You know, about my money...
也许我可以分一点
Maybe I could give a little
给别人
to someone.
去帮助别人
You know, to help out.
这是你的钱 我只是替你保管 像银行一样
It's your money.  I'm just holding it for you, like a bank.
但我比银行好
Except better than a bank
银行经常会被抢劫
because banks always get knocked off.
没人抢得了老托尼
No one knocks off old Tony.
此外 把钱存进银行
Besides, with a bank...
有成吨的狗屁表格要填
there's always tons of forms and all that shit.
在我这儿 不用看
But old Tony, nothin' to read,
不用写
nothin' to write.
都在我脑子里
It's all in his head.
现在我能识字了
I know how to read now.
那很好 里昂 很好
That's good, Leon, good.
你的钱在这儿 你需要
Your money's here.  Whenever you want it,
就来问我拿 这里有一千元
you just ask me. Here's a grand.
- 拿着 - 没事 我不需要
- Come on.  - It's okay.  I don't need it.
拿去吧 找点乐子 拿着
Take it.  Have some fun.  Go ahead.
谢谢
Thank you.
好了
All right.
现在我们来谈谈生意 别走
Now let's talk business. Don't move.
我去拿资料
I'll go get the file.
马诺洛 给我朋友里昂来杯牛奶
Manolo, a glass of milk for my friend Leon here.
听着 玛蒂尔达 你最好小心点
Listen, Mathilda, you better be careful.
不要随便跟街上的陌生人讲话
You can't just speak to any guy off the street.
里昂 紧张什么 这他妈有什么大不了的
Leon, get a grip.  What's the big fucking deal?
我只是在等你的时候 借根烟抽抽
I was just smoking a butt while I was waiting.
我不许你讲脏话
I want you to stop cursing.
你不能总这样和别人交谈
You can't talk to people like that all the time.
我要你学着好好讲话
I want you to make an effort to talk nice.
还有 我希望你把烟戒了 这会要了你的命的
And I want you to stop smoking.  It will kill you.
好的
Okay
离他远一点 他不像好人
Stay away from him.  He looks like a weirdo.
好的
Okay
我五分钟后出来 站在我能看见你的地方
I'll be out in five minutes.  Stand where I can see you.
好的
Okay
里昂 我好像有点爱上你了
Leon, I think I'm kinda falling in love with you.
我第一次有这种感觉
It's the first time for me, you know.
你从没谈过恋爱 你怎么知道这就是爱
How do you know it's love if you've never been in love before?
因为我感觉到了
Cause I feel it.
哪儿
Where?
在我的胃里
In my stomach.
暖暖的
It's all warm.
我以前老是胃疼 现在不会了
I always had a knot there, and now it's gone.
玛蒂尔达 我很高兴你的胃病好了
Mathilda, I'm glad you don't have a stomachache anymore.
但这不能说明什么
I don't think it means anything.
我要迟到了 我最讨厌迟到了
I'm late for work.  I hate being late for work.
嗨 小提琴练得怎么样了
Hey, How's the practicing going?
今天怎么样 小姐
How are we today, miss?
我有点厌倦练琴了
A little sick of practicing.
我懂
I understand.
但是你做得很好
But you're doing all right.
没有人来投诉你们
I haven't received any complaints.
我在弦上放了块布来减少噪音
I put a cloth over the strings to lessen the noise.
真聪明
That's very smart.
不是人人都爱音乐的
Not everyone loves music.
我知道
I know.
你父亲到底是做什么的
What exactly does your father do?
他是作曲家
He's a composer.
真厉害
That's wonderful.
不过他其实不是我父亲
Except he's not really my father.
他是我爱人
He's my lover.
我要去散步了
Think I'll go for a walk.
周六晚上你有事吗
What are you doing Saturday night?
一起吃晚餐怎么样
What about dinner?
你要去哪里
Where you goin'?
拜访6楼J室的朋友
Visiting friends at 6J.
去吧
Go ahead.
犯罪现场禁止入内
我们知道你是个大忙人
We know you're a busy man.
我们也想快点完事
We'll make this short.
你一步一步说清楚
If you'll just take us step- by- step
这里到底发生了什么
through exactly what happened.
那家伙在这儿 他要去拿他的枪
The guy was here.  He went for his gun.
砰的一声 我们打中了他
Bang, we shot him.
孩子们当时在哪里
Where exactly were the kids?
我哪知道
I don't know!
你不觉得他们当时应该在学校么
They should have been at school, don't you think?
你的陈述里面说你是第一个进入屋子的人
Your statement said you were the first man in.
难道你没看见孩子么
Didn't you see any kids?
大门也坏了 发生了什么
The door was broken.  What happened?
你是按程序来的么
Did you follow the procedure?
我失去了一个好队员
I lost a good man here.
你他妈的到底想让我怎么样
What the fuck do you want with me?
配合
Cooperation.
我没时间在这里跟你们扯淡
I haven't got time for this Mickey Mouse bullshit!
你想让我配合你工作 来我办公室 4602
You want cooperation? Come up in my office, room 4602.
孩子就应该去上学
Kids should be at school.
拜托 那是我的球
Come on, that's my ball!
还给我 你去哪儿
Give that back.  Where you goin'?
该死 你干什么 那是我的球
Damn! Where you goin', man? That's my ball!
跟着那辆蓝色的车
Follow the blue car.
你是让我在鸣警笛的车面前闯红灯么
You want me to blast the music and go through the lights?
不 慢慢开
No, drive slowly.
拿着这一百块 他妈的给我闭嘴
Take the hundred bucks, and shut the fuck up.
我不想和你打 但我别无选择
I do not want to fight you, but you leave me no choice.
好孩子 你提醒了我
Boy, you just gave me a great idea!
这办法太好了
I mean a big one!
欢迎回到E频道 现在是每日新闻
Welcome back to E! News Daily...
现在让我们用30分钟的时间回顾一下娱乐大事件
our 30- minute look at the latest in entertainment news.
我是碧昂卡·费拉尔
I'm Bianca Ferrar.
这是给你的 一份礼物
It's for you.  A present.
想打开么 我来开
Do you want me to open it? I'll open it.
怎么样 喜欢么
How do you like it? Nice, eh?
麦高芬先生
Mr.  McGuffin?
我能跟你谈谈么
Can I have a word with you?
这个是合同 两万
Here.  It's for a contract.  Twenty grand, right?
他叫诺曼·史丹菲尔德 他住在4602
His name is Norman Stansfield, and he's in room 4602...
联邦广场26号缉毒大楼4602
in the D. E. A.  Building, 26 Federal Plaza.
我不收
I'm not taking it.
为什么
Why not?
钱太多了
It's too heavy.  Well.
你的枪能租给我用一天吗
Will you rent me your gear for the day?
我的枪从不外租
I never lend out my gear.
但你不是有自己的枪么 用那个
But you still have your gun.  Use it.
帮我个忙 别打碎玻璃
Just do me a favor.  Don't shoot out the window.
你对我怎么这么吝啬
Why are you so mean to me?
你随便杀一些毫不在意的人
Wildly killing people you don't give a shit about...
但就是不帮我解决那些杀了我全家的人
but you won't get the bastards that killed my whole family?
一旦开始复仇 就不会有好结果的
Revenge is not good once you're done.
相信我 还是忘了好
Believe.  It's better to forget.
忘了 在我看到地板上
Forget? After I've seen the outline
我弟弟尸体的轮廓之后
of my brother's body on the floor...
你竟然想让我全都忘了
you expect me to forget?
我要杀了那些狗杂种们
I want to kill those sons of bitches.
爆他们的头
Blow their fucking heads off.
在你杀了人之后
Nothing's the same
一切都会不一样
after you've killed someone.
你的人生会被完全改变
Your life is changed forever.
你的余生恐怕都得睁一只眼闭一只眼睡觉了
You have to sleep with one eye open for the rest of your life.
我他妈才不在意怎么睡觉 里昂
I don't give a shit about sleeping, Leon.
我要爱 或死
I want love or death.
就这样
That's it.
我选择死亡
I want death.
玛蒂尔达 放过我吧 我对你的游戏已经感到厌倦了
Get off my case, Mathilda.  I'm tired of your games.
这是个很棒的游戏 里昂
There's this really great game, Leon.
让人变得聪明 学会思考
Makes people nicer.  Starts them thinking.
你喜欢的那种游戏
The kind of game you love.
如果我赢了 你一辈子都不能离开我
If I win you keep me with you for life.
如果你输了呢
And if you lose?
你就可以像以前一样自己去买东西
Go shopping alone, like before.
玛蒂尔达 你一定会输的
You're gonna lose, Mathilda.
子弹上膛了 我听出来的
There's a round in the chamber.  I heard it.
那又怎样
So what?
要是我在你面前被子弹爆了头 会怎样
What's it to you if I end up with a bullet in the head?
不会怎样
Nothing.
里昂 我希望你说的是实话
I hope you're not lying, Leon.
我真的希望 在你内心深处对我没有一丝的爱
I really hope that deep down inside there's no love in you.
因为只要在你心里 对我有一丝的爱
Because if there is just a little bit of love in there for me...
几分钟之后
I think that in a few
你就会后悔没有阻止我
minutes you'll regret you never said anything.
我爱你 里昂
I love you, Leon.
我赢了
I win.
我受伤了 需要一个帮手
I took a hit.  I need a hand now.
我知道你担心她太年轻 但是她学得很快
I know she's young, but she learns fast.
学习要从娃娃抓起 不是么
Kids need to be shaped into something, right?
我知道 这是我教你的
I know.  I taught you that.
但我们不是有年龄限制么
But ain't there an age limit?
她18岁了
She's 18.
真的么
Really?
托尼 来点喝的吧
How about something to drink, Tony?
当然 马诺洛 给里昂来杯牛奶
Sure.  Manolo, glass of milk for Leon.
很棒的刺青
Nice tattoo.
马诺洛 来两杯
Manolo, make that two.
那是干嘛的
What's that for?
感冒了可不好
Can't afford to catch cold.
首先 你得先找到门链子
First you find out where the chain is.
你看不着 但用手能摸出来
You can't see it, but you can feel it.  Here.
我一按门铃 你就说话
I'll ring, you start talking.
我要说什么
What do I say?
什么都行
Whatever you want.
谁啊
Yes?
我 苏珊
It's Susan.
不好意思 你走错了 小姑娘
I'm sorry.  You must have the wrong door, little girl.
我不认识一个叫苏珊的
I don't know any Susan.
你往后站 我看不见
Move back a little.  I can't see anything.
灯坏了 这里很黑
The light's out.  It's all dark out here.
先生 我好害怕
Mister, I'm scared.
好啦好啦
Okay.
你他妈在干嘛
What the fuck are you doing?
张嘴
Open up.
枪管离开你的嘴我就扣下扳机 明白吗
If it leaves your mouth, I'll pull the trigger, capisce?
对 就这样 松开 我让你松开
Here's okay.  Let it go.  I said, "Let it go. "
去 去那边
Move.  Move over.
放松 别激动
Easy.  Easy.
去吧 该你了
Go ahead.  Your turn.
救命 求你别打我
Help me.  Please don't beat me.
先生
Sir?
先生 那不是我的毒品
Sir, it's not my dope.
先生 看
Sir, look l...
请往左边站点好么
A little left, please.  Sir, look l...
为了保险起见
Now, the security shot.
不 第二枪要打在胸部上方一点
No, the second goes higher on the chest.
瞄准心脏和肺
Aim for the heart and lungs.
这儿 看到了么
There.  Right there.  You see?
第一枪让他倒地
The first shot takes him out of order.
第二枪让他归西
The second finishes him off.
千万别打脸
Never in the face.
雇主认不出他要杀的人 不会付钱的
If they can't recognize the client, you don't get paid.
因为你可以随便杀一个人交差
You could take out anybody and said you did the job.
懂了么
Got it?
懂了 不打脸
Got it.  Never in the face.
你现在可以把工具收起来了
Now you can put the tools away.
到底怎么回事 先生
What the fuck is going on? Hey, mister!
草 到底怎么回事
What are you fuckin...
你看 当你消音器用得太久的时候
You see, when you use the silencer a lot...
你要在这儿垫块布
you have to put a piece of cloth here...
因为它会发热 然后里面烧起来
because it gets very hot and could burn it inside.
好的
Okay
最好用一块黑色的湿布
A damp, black cloth is the best.
你干什么
What you doing?
我们说过不杀女人和小孩儿
We said no women, no kids.
你知道这些毒品会害了谁吗 并不是那些混混 地痞
Who do you think this is gonna kill, junkies and monkeys?
这样就干净了
Now it's clean.
走吧
Let's get out of here.
我还以为我们没权利喝酒呢
I thought we don't have the right to drink.
是 但是今天为你第一次干活破一次例
I know, but we're making an exception for your first time.
既然我们可以为工作成果而破例
Well, if we're making exceptions for a job well- done...
那不如像电影一样 轻轻吻一下
how about a kiss, like in the movies?
不可以
No.
可以
Yes.
你要干嘛
What you doing?
我要亲你
I'm going to kiss you.
不要这样 不要
I want you to stop, please.
来吧 就亲一下
Come on.  Just a kiss.
快停下来 大家都看着呢 去坐好
Stop.  Everyone is watching us.  Go sit down.
慢用
Enjoy.
你不相信我 对吧
You don't believe me, do you?
为什么这么说
How's that?
当我说我爱上你了的时候
When I say I'm in love with you.
玛蒂尔达 别说了 我们换个话题好吗
Mathilda, please drop it.  Just change the subject, okay?
好 好 抱歉
Okay.  Okay.  Sorry.
那 你第一次杀人的时候多大
So, how old were you when you made your first hit?
十九岁
Nineteen.
比你早哦
Beat you.
你在做什么
What you doing?
感冒了可不好
Can't afford to catch a cold.
这儿没门铃
There's no doorbell.
那就敲门
So knock on the door.
谁
Yes?
你好 我是来拜访鲁宾先生的...
Hi.  I'm looking for Mr.  Reuben's apartment...
但是走廊里好黑 而且我迷路了
but it's all dark out here in the hall, and I'm lost.
等一下
Just a second.
还想要么 来吧 把你的脸露出来
You want more? Come on.  Show your fucking face.
你们觉得那么简单就能杀了我吗
You think you're going to get me that easily?
遇到这样强硬的对手时 场面肯定不好看
When it's tough like this, you know it's gonna be ugly.
最好快点解决他
Better make it quick or
不然我们就要一直听他废话
else we'll be all day listening to his crap.
混蛋 来吧 让我看看你的脸 娘娘腔
Asshole! Come on, show me your fucking face, faggot!
再来一个口香糖的把戏啊
Come on, gum trick.
嘿 你知道拉环把戏么
Hey，What about the ring trick? You know that one?
拉环把戏吗 来啊混蛋 我等着呢
Ring trick? Come on, asshole.  I'm waiting.
给我看看啊 混账东西
Show it to me, motherfucker.
这就是拉环把戏[手榴弹]
That's the ring trick.
马里奥 你先回理发店吧 我们一会儿再剪
Mario, go back to the barbershop.  We'll finish later.
里昂 你好啊
Hey Leon, what's up?
都解决了吗
All done already?
没呢
No.
这东西比人好啊
Nicer than people, eh?
以前就告诉过你
I told you that.
你遇到麻烦了吗
You got a problem?
没有
No.
拿把椅子来 坐吧
Get the chair.  Sit down.
我最近在想
I was thinking.
如果哪天我遇到不测
If something happens to me someday...
里昂 你不会遇到不测的
Hey, Leon, nothing's gonna happen to you.
你这么无坚不摧 子弹遇见你都会绕道
You're indestructible.  Bullets slide off you.
这些对你来说都是小意思
You play with 'em.
托尼 我考虑了如何处理我的钱
Tony, I thought about my money.
你记得前几天来这儿的女孩么
You remember the girl who came here the other day?
嗯
Yes.
她的名字是玛蒂尔达
Her name is Mathilda.
如果我遭遇不测
If anything happens to me...
我希望你能把我的钱
I'd like you to give her...
给她
my money.
这事包在我身上 里昂
You can count on me, Leon.
谢谢你 托尼
Thank you, Tony.
我很快就回来
I won't be long.
我犯错了吗
Did I do something wrong?
没有 这一单太大了
No.  This one is too big.
是啊 我只能挑你剩下的做 是这样吗
Yeah, and I only get the leftovers, is that it?
玛蒂尔达 我遇见你之后 所有事情都不同了
Mathilda, since I met you everything's been different.
所以我就是想独处一会儿
So I just need some time alone.
你需要一些时间成长
You need some time to grow up a little.
我已经够成熟了 里昂 我只会变老
I finished growing up, Leon.  I just get older.
我正好相反 我已经够老了
For me it's the opposite.  I'm old enough.
但我还不够成熟
I need time to grow up.
妈的
Shit.
快 投篮
Come on! Hustle!
- 好球 - 过来
- Good shot.  - Come on.
你刚搬过来对吧 住在五楼是吗
You're new, aren't you? Fifth floor, right?
你不可以直接坐这儿
You can't sit here like that.
是吗 为什么
Really, why not?
这不是免费的 就像停车要收费
Nothing's free.  Like a parking meter.
你停这儿 就要付钱
When you stop, you pay.
这是规矩
It's the law.
电视里才这样
Only on T. V.
你说什么
What do you say?
没什么 你要多少钱
Forget it.  How much is your meter?
十美元 每月
Ten dollars a month.
有钱找么
Got change?
算了 我一次性给你十个月的钱
Don't worry about it.  We'll do ten for twelve.
就算我付了一年的钱
I'll pay now for the rest of the year.
好的 一年
Okay, a year.
是不是我付了钱
Does paying rent here mean
还得忍受你们 - 额 不是
I have to put up with you guys? - Er, no.
那就哪儿凉快哪儿呆着去吧
So go play somewhere else.
我需要思考
I need to think.
站直点 你是不是不想要你的工作了
Stand up.  Don't you like your job?
吃的
Food.
你去哪里
Where you going?
快递 4602房间
Special delivery, room 4602.
在这签字
Sign here.
周末愉快 姑娘们
Have a nice weekend, girls.
快递是吧 让我猜猜
Special delivery? Let me guess.
中国菜
Chinese?
或者 泰国菜
Thai, maybe?
我知道了 意大利菜
I've got it.  Italian food.
你叫什么名字 宝贝儿
What's your name, angel?
玛蒂尔达
Mathilda.
把这袋东西放地上
I want you to put the sack on the floor.
很好
Good.
现在我希望你告诉我
Now I want you to tell me
你对"意大利菜"的了解
everything you know about Italian food.
别忘了告诉我 那个让你来的厨师的名字
Don't forget the name of the chef who fixed it for me.
没人叫我过来 是我自己要解决问题
Nobody sent me.  I do business for myself.
所以这是个人恩怨 对吗
So this is something personal, is it?
我他妈又做什么了
What filthy piece of shit did I do now?
你杀了我弟弟
You killed my brother.
对不起
I'm sorry.
- 你想和他一起吗 - 不
- And you wanna join him? - No.
人们都一样
It's always the same thing.
当你开始由衷地恐惧死亡时
It's when you start to become really afraid of death...
才开始学会珍惜生活
that you learn to appreciate life.
- 你热爱生活么 宝贝 - 是的
- Do you like life, sweetheart?  - Yes.
很好
That's good.
因为我不喜欢
Because I take no pleasure
杀死一个
in taking a life
不热爱生命的人
if it's from a person who doesn't care about it.
史丹
Stan,
我刚刚到处找你 楼上找遍了
I've been looking all over for you.  I checked upstairs...
怎么了 我现在很忙
What? I'm busy.
是马尔奇 他死了
It's Malky, man.  He's dead.
马尔奇当时在中国人那里帮我们买东西
Malky was makin' a buy for us from the Chinaman.
但他们与这件事无关
But they got nothin' to do with it.
他们告诉我杀手从外面进来
They told me this guy came from the outside.
是个职业杀手 动作麻利 不知道从哪里冒出来
He was a pro. He was fast.  He fuckin' came out of nowhere.
砰 击毙了那个中国人
Boom, shoots the Chinaman dead in two seconds.
别激动 我是警察
Easy, man.  I'm a cop.
然后他转身 对马尔奇说
Then turns around, says something to Malky like...
不杀女人和小孩儿
No women, no kids.
我觉得这是个人恩怨
I think it was somethin' personal.
今天的死神
Death is
让人捉摸不透
whimsical today.
布拉德
Blood,
你在听我说吗
do you hear me?
是的 我听着呢 史丹 别激动
Yeah, I hear you, Stan.  Just chill out, man.
你能把她带到我的办公室吗
Would you take her up to my office?
可以
All right, yeah.
我滴个上帝啊
Jesus fucking Christ.
"亲爱的里昂
"Leon, my love.
我找到杀死我弟弟的人了
I know where to find the guys who killed my brother.
他们的上司是诺曼·史丹菲尔德
Their boss is Norman Stansfield.
他在联邦大楼 4602号房间
He's in the D. E. A.  Building, room 4602.
我要亲手杀了他 如果我出了什么意外
I'm gonna do them myself.  If something goes wrong,
我在桌上给你留了两万块
I left you 20 grand on the table.
合同规定好的 五千块换一个人头 对吗
It's for a contract.  Five grand a head, right?
只有杀了他我才能安心
I know I'll feel better after I do this.
我爱你 玛蒂尔达"
I love you.  Mathilda. ”
在这儿等我 我去去就来
Wait for me.  I won't be long.
我不能停在这里 这是联邦大楼
I can't park in front like this.  It's a federal building!
他会按我说的做
He's gonna do the same exact thing that I said.
一把九厘米手枪
A nine "Millie".
子弹 又一把九厘米手枪
Bullets. Another nine "Millie".
你带着这些枪是要干嘛
What'd you plan to do with all these guns?
她也许是想拿下整栋楼呢
Maybe she was planning on taking out the whole building.
天啊 看这是什么 中饭
Holy shit! What we got here? Lunch.
小心点 布拉德 可能有毒
Careful, Blood, might be poisoned.
1991年 加州发生食用鳀鱼导致海鸟死亡的多莫酸中毒事件
不会的 上面又没有鳀鱼
No,man. There's no anchovies on this.
这就是你所谓的"去去就来"
Is that what you call 'I won't be long'?
我在这儿晃了至少有十分钟
I been hanging around here for at least ten minutes.
我尽快了 走吧
I did my best.
你喜欢吗
Do you like it?
嗯
Yes.
那就说出来
So say it.
我喜欢
I like it.
不渴吗
Not thirsty?
你知道吗 女孩的第一次非常重要
You know, a girl's first time is very important.
这决定了她之后的生活是否性福
It determines the rest of her life sexually.
我在姐姐的杂志上看到的
I read that once in one of my sister's magazines.
我闺蜜告诉我 她们的第一次并不美好
My girlfriends told me they hated their first experience.
因为她们不爱那些男的
That's because they didn't love the guys.
她们那么做只是为了以后炫耀
They just did it to show off.
但后来 她们开始享受了 感觉就像抽烟一样
Afterwards, they started liking it, like cigarettes.
我的第一次会是美好的吗
Will I like it the first time?
玛蒂尔达 不行
Mathilda, no.
为什么不行
Why not?
我就是做不到
I just can't.
你爱着别人吗
You love someone else?
不 我的意思是
No. I mean...
很久之前 在我还没来美国的时候
There was someone a long time ago.
我爱过一个人
Before I came to the States.
她爸爸不希望她和我联系
Her father didn't want her to see me.
她出身名门望族
She was from a very respectable family.
而我家却
Mine was...
你懂的
you know...
没什么名望
not so respectable.
每次她出来见我 她爸爸就会抓狂
Her dad went nuts every time she'd take off to see me.
但她仍然偷偷溜出来见你 对吧
She still snuck off to see you, right?
对
Right.
你看 爱是不可阻挡的 里昂
See, nothing can stop love, Leon.
他杀了她
He killed her.
对着她头部开了一枪
One shot through the head.
他只在监狱待了两天 就被放出来了
They kept him in jail for two days, and they let him go free.
他们说那是场意外
They said it was an accident.
所以
So...
有天晚上 我潜伏着
one night I waited for him.
在五百英尺外 用一支狙击枪
Five hundred feet with a lens.
也让他发生了意外
He also had an accident.
当天晚上 我坐船到了这里
The same night I took a boat and came here...
来投奔我的爸爸 他当时在为托尼工作
to meet up with my father who was working for Tony.
我那时十九岁
I was 19.
从那以后 我就再没离开过这座城市
Since then I've never left the city, and...
也没再谈过恋爱
I've never had another girlfriend.
你懂了吧 玛蒂尔达
You see, Mathilda...
我不会是个好恋人
I wouldn't be a good lover.
好吧
Okay.
你可以答应我一件事吗
Would you do me one favor?
什么
What?
我不想再看到你在椅子上睡觉了
I'm sick of watching you sleep on your chair.
我们同床睡吧
We're gonna share the bed.
我觉得这样不好
I don't think it's a good idea.
就这样 把腿放到床上 对
It's okay. Put your legs up on the bed. Yeah.
不错 非常好
Yeah.  That's nice.
躺好 就这样 放松点
Put your head down.  It's okay.  Relax.
晚安 里昂
Good night, Leon.
晚安
Good night.
马诺洛 把孩子们带进厨房
Manolo, take the kids in the kitchen.
我很尊重你的事业 托尼
I have a lot of respect for your business, Tony.
你以前帮我们杀人的时候
When you've killed for us in the past...
从没让我们失望过
we've always been satisfied.
正因为如此
That's exactly why today
今天我非常为难
is going to be very hard for me.
希望你能体谅我的情绪
I hope you'll excuse my mood.
我的人就在你的地盘上被杀了
My man was killed right here on your turf.
中国佬告诉我
The Chinks tell me that the hit man...
杀手有点像意大利人
was kind of the Italian type.
所以我们想 托尼也许知道些什么
So we figured that Tony might know something.
等等
Wait.
听我说完 还有更精彩的呢
There's more. You're gonna love this.
几小时之后 一个十二岁的小女孩
A few hours later, a little 12- year- old girl
全副武装地 闯进我办公的地方
comes into my office armed to the teeth,
铁了心地
with the firm intention
要把我送进太平间
of sending me straight to the morgue.
你知道下午从我的地盘上把她救出去的人
Do you know who came and got her in the middle of the afternnon right there
是谁吗
in my building?
就是那个意大利杀手
The very same Italian hit man.
我特别想会一会他
I'm dying to meet him.
别紧张 一切正常
Relax.  Everything's fine.
睡得好吗
Sleep well?
我从没真正睡着过
I never really sleep.
一直不敢睡得太熟
Got one eye open always.
是哦 我忘了
Yeah, I forgot.
我可从没见过谁
I never saw someone
睡得不熟 呼噜还能打得这么响
with one eye open snore so much.
我打呼了？
I snore?
像个婴儿一样
Like a baby.
我去买些牛奶当早餐 很快就回来
I'm gonna get some milk for breakfast.  I won't be long.
回来时别忘了暗号
Don't forget the code when you come back.
两下 一下 然后再两下 对吧
Two knocks, then one, and two knocks again.  Right?
对
Right.
先生您好 算算这些多少钱 我去拿点牛奶
Hello, Signore.  Ring these up.  I'm gonna go get some milk.
从现在起不许出声
From here on out, you don't make a sound.
你需要回答我的问题
You answer my questions by nodding yes
点头肯定 摇头否定 明白了吗
or shaking your head no.  You got it?
他只有一个人吗
Is he alone?
他在等你吗
Does he expect you?
你有房间的钥匙吗
Do you have keys to the apartment?
你们之间有识别身份的敲门暗号吗
Is there a code, a way of knocking, so he knows it's you?
阿尔法队
Alpha team.
已就位 准备就绪
Final position.  We're ready to go.
小心点
Be careful.
退后 退后
Move! Move!
该死
Shit.
阿尔法队 人员伤亡 人员伤亡
Alpha team.  Man down.  Man down.
我提醒过你了
I told you.
本尼
Benny.
把所有人都找来
Bring me everyone.
所有人是什么意思
What do you mean, "Everyone"?
每个人！！！
Everyone!
拿着这个
Take this.
去看一眼
Go take a look.
别动
Don't move.
你看见什么了
Do you see anything?
是他
It's the guy.
他就在这儿 拿枪指着我的头
He's here.  He's got a gun to my head.
知道了 大家都别动
Ok.  Nobody moves.
把那女孩放了
Let the girl go.
兄弟 冷静点
Take it easy, man!
把那女孩放了
Let the girl go.
好的 我们放她走
Okay, the girl's comin' out.
把这女孩放了
Let the girl go.
把斧子从墙上取下来 在那儿 快去
Grab the axe off the wall.  Over there.  Go!
你得跟我们走
You're coming with us.
天哪 他冲他开枪了
Christ, he shot him!
混蛋
Bastard!
闪 闪 闪 闪
Move! Move! Move! Move!
去把这该死的水关了
Shut the fucking water off!
明白
Got it.
过来
Come
我们处于劣势
We're in a bad way here.
派人进来 再说一遍 派人进来
Send the cats. I repeat,sent the cats.
我不知道是怎么回事
I don't know what happened.
我没看到他们进来 我发誓
I didn't see 'em coming, I swear!
我只是去买东西
I just went shopping
回来的时候 他们就把楼封锁了
and I came back, and they were everywhere.
不要靠近窗户
Stay away from the window.
里昂
Leon.
过来
Come here.
是狙击手
Snipers.
现在 把那个混蛋给我抓出来
Okay, now, get this fucking asshole out of there.
我们要怎么出去
How are we gonna get outta here now?
交给我吧 是时候退房了
Leave it to me.  We're checking out.
但是里昂 这儿对你来说太窄了
But Leon it's not big enough for you.
只能勉强够我钻进去
It's barely big enough for me.
说好了都听我的
We said no discussion.
不 我不会抛下
No, I'm not letting...
我不走 我绝对不走
I'm not going! I won't go!
听我说
Listen to me.
我们一起的话 没有逃生的可能
We have no chance together.
但如果我单独行动 就能逃掉
But if I'm alone, I can do it.
相信我 我很强的 玛蒂尔达
Trust me.  I'm in good shape, Mathilda.
我在托尼那儿存了一大笔钱 一大笔
I know I've got a lot of money with Tony, a lot.
我们带上那笔钱一起远走高飞
We'll take it and leave together,
就我们两个人 好吗 快走
just the two of us. Okay? Go.
不要 你只是在安慰我而已
No!You're saying that so I won't worry.
我不想失去你 里昂
I don't wanna lose you, Leon.
你不会失去我的 玛蒂尔达
You're not gonna lose me, Mathilda.
你让我体会到生命的真谛
You've given me a taste for life.
我想要做快乐的人 睡在床上 落地生根
I wanna be happy, sleep in a bed, have roots.
我不会再让你孤身一人
You'll never be alone again.
求你了 快走吧 宝贝儿 快走
Please, go now, baby.  Go.
冷静点 快离开这儿 去吧
Calm down.  Go now.  Go.
我们在托尼那儿见 我会把他们全部杀掉
See you at Tony's.  I'm gonna clean them all.
一小时后托尼那儿见
Tony's in an hour.
我爱你 玛蒂尔达
I love you, Mathilda.
我也爱你 里昂
I love you, too, Leon.
喂 楼上他妈的在干什么
Hey, what the fuck is going on up there?
我只说要抓住那个男的 不是让你们拆了这栋操蛋的楼
I just said "Take the guy out", not the fucking building.
这儿还有一个活人
We've got one breathing here!
快叫医生
Get a medic on the horn!
这里有一个伤员 让一下
We've got a wounded man.  Make way!
把他送下楼
Down those stairs.
下来 快点
Let's go! Move!
把伤员送下楼 放在担架上
Get that guy off the stairs! Lay him on the layer.
让你的人退到那儿去
Get your team back out there!
有两名队员要下楼 抓紧时间
We've got two men comin' down the stairs.  Let's hurry!
你还好吗 嘿 这里需要一个医生
You okay? Hey, I need a medic over here!
快滚过去
Move your fuckin' asses.
第一小队 房间里现在是什么情况
Squad Number One, what's the status on the apartment?
烟太浓了 屁都看不见
Can't see shit.  Too much smoke.
再给我们五分钟
Give us five minutes.
好的 去吧
Okay.  You got it.
什么 两百个大汉
What? Two hundred men
还找不到一个男人和一个小女孩吗 找到小女孩了吗
can't find one man and a girl? Did you find the girl?
嗨 感觉怎么样 把你的面罩摘下来 快
Hi, how are you doing? Take your mask off, quick.
让我检查一下你的伤口 很深啊 好 再检查一下这里的伤口
Let me see you.  That's deep.  Right.  And this one here...
你是第三警区来的吗
You're from the 3rd Precinct?
来把他的袖子稍微弄开一点
Let's open up his sleeve a little bit.
没事了 放下吧 换这只手
All right, fine.  Put it down.  This one.
在这儿等两分钟 我马上回来
You stay there for two minutes.  I'll be right back.
让我把面罩带上 这样呼吸更顺畅一点
Let me put the mask back on.  I breathe better with it.
好的 你不会有事的 坐着别动
OK.  You're all right.  Sit tight.
快点 所有人都出去
Come on, everybody out!
走走走 都出去
Let's go! Out!
哥们 给他让条道
Clear the way, men.
你在这儿干什么呢 赶紧离开 快
What are you doing here? Get out.  Come on.
史丹菲尔德吗
Stansfield?
静候差遣
At your service.
这个是
This is from...
替玛蒂尔达给的
Mathilda.
妈的
Shit.
里昂说 如果出事了就让我帮你一把
Leon asked me to help you out if somethin' happened,
我想应该是出事了 对吧
and I think somethin' happened, right?
他为你留了点钱
He put aside a little cash for you.
我是这么想的
So what I'm suggesting is that...
你还这么年轻
seein' as how you're still so young...
所以在你长大之前 就由我来替你保管这笔钱吧
I should hold the money for you until you're older.
你懂的 就像银行一样 只不过
Like a bank, you know, except...
我这儿比银行更保险 因为银行总会破产
it's better than a bank 'cause banks always get knocked off.
而老托尼始终屹立不倒
No one knocks off old Tony.
不过这毕竟是你的钱 在这期间
But it's your money.  In the meantime...
你只需要隔三差五来这儿一次
all you gotta do is come here every once in a while...
从我这儿取点钱去找乐子 好吗
and I'll dish it out so you can have a little fun, OK?
开始就先给你一百块吧
Here's a hundred bucks to start.
我不能在这儿工作吗
Can't I get a job instead?
你说工作
A job?
你又能做些什么鬼
What the hell can you do?
我会杀人
I can clean.
我这儿可没有能让十二岁小孩做的工作
I ain't got no work for a 12- year- old kid...
别再有这样该死的想法了
so get it out of your goddamn head!
都结束了 游戏结束了 里昂死了
It's over! The game's over!Leon's dead!
听懂了没
You hear me?
好了 你觉得我就不难过吗
Come on.  You think I ain't hurtin' too?
但是他已经死了
But he's dead.
你得把这些破事儿都忘了
You're gonna forget all this craziness
然后好好滚回学校念书 懂了吗
and get your little ass back to school, capito?
现在拿上这些钱 快滚吧
Now take this money and get the hell outta here.
这个月内别让我再看到你的脸
Don't let me see your face till next month...
因为我感觉
'cause something tells me
我一直以来的好脾气就快崩不住了
I'm about to lose my famous kind streak.
斯宾塞学校
我的父母
My parents...
四周前在车祸中丧生
died in a car accident four weeks ago.
那太可怕了
It was terrible.
在你第一次来这儿的时候
We didn't have the time
我们没有时间互相了解
to get to know one another when you first came here...
但我希望你能明白
but I want you to know
我绝不会让一个孩子感到失望
I'm not the kind of woman who'd let down a child...
不管她的处境如何 也不管她犯了什么错误
whatever her situation, whatever her mistake.
所以我会帮助你
So I'm going to help you
也真心实意地欢迎你回到这里
and do my best to welcome you here again.
但是我有一个条件
But on one condition:
你必须告诉我实话 玛蒂尔达
You have to stop lying to me, Mathilda.
我希望你能试着相信我
I want you to take a chance and trust me.
现在告诉我到底发生了什么事
Now tell me what happened to you.
好吧
Okay.
我的家人因为毒品纠纷
My family got shot down by D. E. A.  Officers...
被缉毒组的警察开枪打死了
because of a drug problem.
一个世界上最好的男人带我逃走了
I left with the greatest guy on Earth.
他是一个职业杀手 在镇上首屈一指
He was a hit man, the best in town,
但是今天早上他死了
but he died this morning.
如果你不帮我的话
If you don't help me,
可能我今晚就会死掉
I'll be dead by tonight.
你们认识她吗
You know her?
从来没见过
I've never seen her.
我想我们能在这儿安心生活了 里昂
I think we'll be okay here. Leon.